<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Page-rsses on theDB</title>
    <link>https://dbolella.github.io/page/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Page-rsses on theDB</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>dbolella@gmail.com (Danny Bolella)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>dbolella@gmail.com (Danny Bolella)</webMaster>
    <atom:link href="https://dbolella.github.io/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>https://dbolella.github.io/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>dbolella@gmail.com (Danny Bolella)</author>
      <guid>https://dbolella.github.io/page/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;My name is Danny Bolella.  I&amp;rsquo;m a Developer/Scrum Master who just wants to do what I love!  And coding just so happens to be one of those things.  For why I&amp;rsquo;ve created this blog, just out &lt;a href=&#34;../../post/2016-09-30-welcome/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-history&#34;&gt;my history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I graduated from Stevens Insitute of Technology in 2012 with a B.S. in Computer Science.  While at Stevens, I participated in the Cooperative Education program, which earned me 2 years of full-time work experience across 3 companies.  I graduated not only with everything I learned in the classroom, but also the invaluable lessons and experiences I had working on real projects ranging from private equity tracking, to energey forecasting, to routing systems for oil tankers travelling across the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I graduated I worked for 2 and a half years in the asset management part of a major bank.  There, I worked as a full stack developer for a handful of internal products.  Eventually, I joined where I am today as an iOS developer where I worked on the flagship mobile application responsible for millions of dollars in transactions.  My journey here has put me in the middle of a major agile transformation where I&amp;rsquo;ve practicaed pair programming, TDD, setting up and maintaing continuous integration processes, and working in sprints.  When the opportunity to take on a more leadership role presented itself, I took it and am now a Scrum Master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve completed my Certified Scrum Master training under Dr. Jeff Sutherland (co-creator of Scrum).  My focus now is to not only continue to expand my knowledge of good software craftmanship but also agile as it applies on the team and enterprise levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;interests&#34;&gt;interests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;technology&#34;&gt;Technology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I&amp;rsquo;ve really been interested in Swift and node.js these days.  Node because it has so many uses and it&amp;rsquo;s quick and raw to work with.  And Swift because I&amp;rsquo;ve totally immersed my self in the iOS/Apple ecosystem now, but also because I&amp;rsquo;m one of those on the bandwagon who feel that the language is hopeful.  I truly believe it can be a great language that can be fun, elegant, and powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;agile&#34;&gt;Agile&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a relatively young scrum master, I&amp;rsquo;m working to learn everything I can about agile and scrum.  The purpose is to not only know what the heck it is I&amp;rsquo;m doing, but also to know where we can be/are heading.  I&amp;rsquo;m fascinated by the prospect that we can all work in more fulfilling and purposeful ways while getting more work done with less time/energy/resources.  My passion to be a servant leader and put others first drives my interest in agile.  I want to see others succeed and flourish, and being a scrum master is a way I can help that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>